amb
in
casc R Ow viable
[Musika]
vi
occ at the east and west
[Musika]
sides babad ako babad ako ngayon wo
oh s
na Malen Malen
this session is call to order my esteem colleagues you requested to stand for the singing
of the national anthem bang magiliw per
Silanganan alam ng puso sa mo'y buhay lupang
hinirang
[Musika]
kaul isil saral at bundok sa simoy at sa langit k poha may hilang ang tula at
awit sa paglayang nin mahal ang kisap ng watawat Moy tagumpay na nilingi angi
tuwing ng araw niya kailan pangay maniling Lupa ng araw nang w Amit kongs
kay a langit sa aming
Layan naat may mga apit ang mamatay ng dahil
[Musika]
SAO may request team colleagues to remain
standing for prayers to be led by Congress person first District of
Sorsogon representative Marie bernadeth G Escudero um Let us put ourselves in the presence
of God in the name of the father and of the son and of the holy spirit amen as We Come Together this afternoon Let us
take a moment to reflect on the purpose that brings us here we all come from different Walks of Life with different
belief and perspectives yet we share a common goal to serve the philipino people with integrity and care in this
Spirit I ask that we open our hearts to standing and Our minds to wisdom May our discussions today be guided by respect
patience and a genuine desire to do what is right for those we represent Let us remember the responsibility we hold and
the impact of our decisions on the lives of so many May we approach our work with humility in a sincere commitment to
fairness and justice above all Let us strive to work together in a way that honors shared humanity and the values we
all Cherish kindness honesty and a commitment to the greater good this we
pray in Jesus name Amen Salamat con person Mar bernadet GSO
distri majority leader please Mr Speaker I mve that we call the of members secretary general is directed to call
the role of members please R of members honorable representatives Abalos
abante Abunda Aaron
idre akop Adong
advincula agaro Alba Albano
Al Mario Almonte
Alonte Alvarez J Alvarez Mercedes Alvarez
pantalon amante amatong ang angara Aquino Aquino Magsaysay
arbison Arenas arrogancia Asistio aide
aumentado balindong Barba barbers baronda
baskug Bautista Bautista Lim Benitez bernos billones biron bolilia bondok
bongalon Bordado bosita Briones Brosas buhain
bul Bustos cabredo cagas kahayon Uy calderon Calixto Campos
kawagan cardema cari Castro France Castro J Celeste Chan
chato Chua chungalao ko Angelica Natasha
Elizar jaim ard Colada colantes corvera Cruz ambrosio
Cruz Ricardo kua quaresma dagooc dalipe dalog dayanghirang
Daza de Jesus divinia Defensor delm de los Santos dimaporo Mohammad kalin
dimaporo City Amina Dionisio Domingo duavit duh Duterte d Faustino ino d
Faustino Michael Carlos d ian paul ecleo emano Enverga Escudero espares Espina
estrelia judela farinas Fernandez Ferrer Antonio Ferrer Juliet Marie Flores fortz
frasco fresnedi Fuentebella galeos Garcia Albert Garcia Dante
J Garcia ang Garcia Pao Garcia Vincent Gardiola
Garin gasataya Gato goed Christopher Gar
Golez Gomez Gonzaga Gonzalez Aurelio Gonzalez Nepal Gonzalez
sanda wi gulas Gutierrez haresco
hataman Hernandez Herrera orata Javier ko olga ar co Ricardo co wilton
kon hun labadlabad lakon lakon Noel Lagman lagon dafne
lagon s Lara lazatin Lee ligarda libanan Lim kay
Loyola luistro lumayag makapagal aroyo Maeda madrona magsino malapitan
mangawang manikis Manuel maranon marcoleta Marcos Mariano Hernandez Marino Marquez
Martinez mastura matibag matugas Mendoza
mercado mercado Revilla Miguel mom morden nava nisay nograles Juan Fidel
Felipe nograles Margarita Nolasco oaminal olazo
Olivarez ongchuan ordanes Ortega uan Dizon padernos paduano paglas Palma
panaligan Pancho panotes Pascual penya Pimentel Plaza plo prisa sa gabas
pumaren puno kimbo Rama rhena remulla Revilla Bry Revilla Ramon Jolo Reyes
rilo Rivera Robes Rodriguez iloio Rodriguez rufus Roman Romero romualdes
Ferdinand Martin romualdes yeda Marie romualdo Romulo Roque sakdalan
sagarbarria sali salimbangon salo Santos saulog
Silverio sson richel sson Ronald Singson mihan Solon suan Suansing Horacio
Suansing Mikaela Angela Suarez talado Tamayo tambunting Tan Joseph Tan Kei
micaa Tan reynolds Michael tan samir tan Stephen James Tan tambut tanchay tanco
tariel Teodoro tevez tianco tieng Tolentino Tulfo
Erwin Tulfo Joselyn tool for Ralph wendel Tupas tutor t Umali unabia ungab
Uy valeriano valmayor Vargas Vargas Alfonso Velasco Veloso
Tuazon Vergara verzosa Villa Villafuerte Luis Raymond Villafuerte megga Luis vill
Nueva Villar villaraza suz vill Rica violago yamsuan Yap Crisel yap
christopherson yap edv yap Eric y Divina Grace y jasel Victoria yulo Zamora
Amparo maria zamar maria Carmen zamara Isabel Maria Zubiri
sige sige Mr Speaker the roll call shows that
210 members responded to the Call
Salamat secret general with 210 members responding to the call the ch declares the presence of majority leader please
speaker considering that copies of journal number 5 dated august 6 2024 already distributed to members I to
dispense withour objection the chair here is None
the motion is approved the reading of the said journal is dispensed with and the journal number 5 dated august 6 2004
is here by approved majority
leader Mr Speaker I would like to acknowledge the guests of Representative Attorney JV
of the second District of Batangas the visitors from the municipality of San Pascual Batangas Barangay treasurers
League Isabel catubay Gina Andaya imu kusi jer
abratique Annalyn Hernandez Veron corn Diana Ramos Diana calingasan Sherry De
Chavez Sally Wong Ross Padilla jonal de Leon vinus sumadsad Michelle monato Rose
Mendoza Lee Padilla aelia adarlo jocely
abanto manel Quinto Rosalinda Zelda Eden Panopio Jenny sempron and District staff
Zoo silang JR Anna Regie helera Nicki hea Andre cheris Blanco
Thank you to the guest of Congress person honorable Attorney JV jinkx R lis
straw from the municipality of San Pascal second District of Batangas Welcome on behalf of speaker Martin
rales Welcome To The House of Representative hapon Thank
you majority leader Mr Speaker I would like to acknowledge The Guest of the honorable Faustino Michael d the thd Uh
5th District of Isabela from the municipality of Aurora
ah tomasito guab pipito Valenzuela
marcelina ganotice Leonardo Peralta marl lacambra Melvin Rey galingana Rogelio
cabarubias rly Fajardo Noel abugan Robert Marquez Rolly V Duque
Ronald V pabro leonel piso Roger Alejandro lolito corbito simplicio
ramiro Jesus lantano Robert sagadraca
Antonio Benito Mijares Orlando padaong Samuel
Marquez Lazaro Rey J Rolando sambrano
Erwin Regal John mangati Mario labasan sal ramiscal Michael R
Santos Rolando Marquez are the punong Barangay of municipality of Aurora and
the Barang of the municipality of Luna Ramos William galotera Elsa Gonzalez
Orlando and Lucas Denis edmilao Bernardo Isidro Antonio valeriano
herson Madriaga Veronica omnes Joselito
fontanilla lauter bukag Noli bitayo Fidel rumbo mero del alejo Ronald m
Ramil lowel C Perez jeffre ramores
V mity of aur speaker Thank you maj leer to the guest of hon Faustino
Michael to the Barang Chairman and sk officials from Isabella fth legislative
District municipality of Aurora and Luna on behalf of speaker Martin Welcome to
the house of representatives Thank
you majority leader Mr Speaker I move that we recognize the guests of the
honorable phon espares of the coop Nat party List namely the transport coop
leaders namely Mel melas Edwin bosos rebeca Antonio Mar
Anthony marl Ramos rosalan shery Flores Helen
alcantara Anna Andres Helen repon sar Pagunsan yole de los Santos Rose Adarna
villablanca frida Flores esteso Mariel Silvia
Magtibay Heidi Manuel Helen Tugas Gilbert
sorano Samonte jaimeer Teresa antio janita abando Julie laesa Sheila
Bautista marl Mejia Mary Anne dela cruz sheril lu ruelo Jenelyn bacarisas
Marlene senden Leonard Bautista Ruel cura Yolanda pinzon Jason valerio and Jess
kiroz Thank you majority leader to the guest of honorable filimon MS parz of
coop natco part list to the leaders of transport coop leaders Welcome on behalf
of speaker Martin romales Welcome to the house of representatives Magandang
hapon Thank you majority
leader Mr Speaker considering JN number aug
724 were already distributed to the members I to dispense with the reading there and subsequently to approve the
journal so Mr Speaker is no obje the ch here the motion is appr the reading of
the journal is dispensed with journal number dated aug 7 2024
is majority leader Mr Speaker ive that we proceed with the
reference of business and wish that secretary general be directed to read the titles of bills and
resolutions on first reading as well as communications and committee reports Is there any objection the ch he now the secretary general ised
to B resolutions reading as communications and committee reports for referral for the appropriate
committee please reference of business bills on first reading House Bill
1075 banning Pogo and other operations related there to by representative Villanueva to the committee on games and
amusement House Bill 1077 establishing the summer Island region by representative
libanan to the committee local government House Bill 1078 renewing for another 25 years the
franchise granted to the spere entertainment incorporated formerly benget Broadcasting Corporation by
representative nograles Margarita the comm legislative franchises House Bill 1071 strengthening cyber crime
prevention measures amending the cyber crime prevention Act of 2012 by representative rul to the committee on
information and communications technology House Bill 1073 providing for the creation of more
school buildings and infrastructures by representative Romero to the committee on Basic Education and culture House Bill 1074
strengthening the National Book development board amending the book Publishing industry development act by representative yamsuan to the committee
on Basic Education and culture House Bill 1075 strengthening the governance of basic educ Increasing the basic
education research fund representative Romero the comme on Basic Education and culture House Bill 1076 to reform and
restructure the energy regulatory Commission by representative puente to the committee on energy
resolutions house resolution 187 congratulating commending and conferring Congressional Medal of distinction to
Carlos yo for winning two gold medals in men's artistic gymnastics individual events at the 2024 Paris Olympics by
representative Olivarez the rules house resolution 1875 congratulating and commending
artistic gymnast Carlos yulo for bagging two gold medals in the 2024 Olympics by representative
Vargas to the committee on rules house resolution 187 commending the 22 Filipino Olympians including double gold
bagger Carlos yulo for their outstanding performance and in the 2024 Paris Olympics and urging
the house to conduct an inquiry on the state of sports development and funding in the Philippines by representatives Castro France Brosas and Manuel the
committee on rules house resolution 1878 recognizing congratulating and commending Carlos yulo for winning two
Olympic gold medals at the 2024 Paris Olympics by representative d Faustino Michael
Carlos rules resolution 1879 calling on the house to congratulate and commend Carlos yulo for
winning two gold medals in the men's artistic gymnastics individual events in the 2024 Olympic Games by representative
t Joseph the committee on rules house resolution 1881 conferring the Congressional Medal of distinction on
Carlos yulo for winning the second and Third Olympic gold medals of the Philippines by representatives Chua
dionicio valeriano Maeda Cheng and abante to the committee on rules house resolution
1882 conferring a Congressional Medal of distinction to Carlos yulo for being the first Southeast Asian to win multiple
Olympic Gold medals by representative salo committee on rules house resolution
1884 commending and congratulating Carlos yulo for winning the first ever two Philippine gold medals in gymnastics
at the men's floor exercise and men's vault at the 20 2 Paris Olympic Games representative
Loyola on rules house resolution 1885 commending and congratulating EJ
obena for his exceptional feet in the men's po vault event at 2024 summer Olympic Games by representative Lee
committee on rules house resolution 1886 expressing profound Congratulations and commendation to Carlos yo for his
exceptional representation of the phines in gymnastics by winning two medals in the 2024 Paris Olympics by
representative Ral wendel rul house resolution 1887
expressing profound Congratulations and commendation to Filipino athlete her badan for her exceptional representation
of the Philippines in women's boxing as an official delegate to the 2024 Paris Olympics representative for Ralph wendel
to the comm on rules house resolution 1888 congratulating and commending Carlos yulo for being the first Filipino
athlete to win two gold medals at the Olympic Games by representative manques to the committee on rules house
resolution 1889 commending and congratulating Filipino boxer Ira Villegas for her exemplar performance in
winning bronze medal in women's boxing 50 kgr division in Paris 2024 summer Olympic Games by representative Lee to
the committee on rules house resolution 1890 commanding Filipino Olympic gymn Carlos yulo for winning two Gold medals
for the men's vaults and men's floor exercise events in the 2024 Olympic Games by representative guico to the
committee rules house resolution 1891 congratulating commending and honoring Ira Vegas for winning the bronze medal
in the women's boxing 50 kgr competition at the 20 24 Olympic Games by representative Cop the comm rules house
resolution 1892 urging the Doh to provide and disseminate free leptospirosis treatments and antitet
shots through the fiel health for areas affected by Super typon karina and other calamities by representatives tulf Josel
and tulf Ralph wend heal house resolution 1893 expressing congratulations to
Filipino athlete Carlos yulo for winning two gold medals in gymnastics at the 2024 Paris Olympics and commending his
resilience and commitment to excellence by representative baronda to the committee on rules house resolution 184
congratulating and commending Carlos yulo for his historic two gold medal wins in the Paris 2024 Olympics by
representative nisai the committee on rules house resolution 1 895 congratulating Ira Cordero Villegas for
winning the bronze medal in women's 50 kgr boxing at the Paris 2024 Olympics by representative sakaluran to the
committee on rules house resolution 1896 expressing The Great Pride and joy of Filipinos in the bronze medal won Ira
Villegas and the 50 kgr division of women's boxing of the 2024 summer Olympic Games by representative tolintino
to the committee on rules house resolution 1897 recommending Carlos yulo to be inducted into the Philippines sports
Hall of Fame in artistic gymnastics by the philippin sports Commission by representative suan to the committee on
rules Youth and stand corrected to the committee on
Youth and sports development Please proceed house resolution 1898 com and congratulating Ira Cordero
Villegas for winning the bronze medal in the women's 50 kgr boxing event at the 2024 Paris Olympic Games by
representative puno to the committee on rules messages from the Senate message dated august 6 2024 informing the house
of representatives that on even date the Senate approved the conference committee report on the disagreeing provisions of Senate bill 2432 and House Bill numbers
3917 and 9284 on the proposed amendments to the anti-aging act of
2016 to the committee on rules message dated August 7 2024 informing the house that on august 6 2024 the Senate
designated senators Tolentino de la Rosa Padilla Cynthia Villar and Pimentel as confer to the conference committee on
the disagreeing provisions of House Bill 6580 creating two additional rtc branches in the fourth judicial region
tob station in Silang Cavite the committee rules message dated August 7 2024
informing the house that on august 6 2024 the Senate designated senators Tolentino de Rosa Padilla Cynthia Villar
and Pimentel as confer to the conference committee on the dising provisions of House Bill 8254 creating five additional rtc
branches in the fourth judicial region to be station in the municipalities of Rosario and San Juan province of batang gas to the committee rules
communications letter dated May 31 2024 of the kaa oic Director 4 cluster 3
legislative judiciary and constitutional offices transmitting to the house of representatives a copy of their special
audit report on expenditures incurred for barangay and sk elections to the committee on public accounts letters
dated June 5 7 10 and 11 2024 of the kaa Regional director Regional Office number 4a furnishing the house with copies of
their annual audit reports for the year ending December 31 2023 on certain water districts government agencies and state
universities to the committee on public accounts letter dated June 6 2024 of the dotr under secretary for Administration
and finance submitting to the house certain reports as of May 31 2024 to the committee on
operations that is dat to June 11 2024 of the kaa oic audit team leaders audit team R 508 and audit team number 02a
transmitting to the house copies of their annual audit reports in the sorsogon state university and Davao Oriental state university respectively
for the year ending December 31 2023 to the committee on public accounts letter dated June 11 2024 of the kaa
audit team leader Regional Office number 11 furnishing the house with copies of their annual audit reports for the year
ending December 31 2023 on certain agencies the committee on public
accounts letter is dated June 13 and 14 2024 of the bsp governor transmitting to the house copies of certain reports
including the bsp 2023 annual report to the committee on banks and financial
intermediaries letter dated June 19 2024 of the gsis President and General Manager submitting to the house a copy
of their gsis investments portfolio as of December 31 2023 to the committee on government
enterprises and privatization letter dated June 19 2024 of the presidential advisor in peace
reconciliation and Unity providing the house with a copy of their accomplishment report for the month of May
2024 to the special committee on peace reconciliation and Unity letter dated June 20 2024 of the kaa
commissioner furnishing the house with copies of their annual audit reports and Management letter on certain government corporations to the committee on public
accounts letter dat to June 2524 of neda secretary providing the house with a copy of their annual report
2023 to the committee on economic Affairs suspended
letters dated June 27 and July 2
Sorry tama naman
last page s resume please proceed letter is
dated June 27 and July 2 2024 of the bsp office of the general council and legal services transmitting to the house jly
certified copies of certain bsp issuances to the committee on banks and financial intermediaries annual audit
report for Cy 2023 and Management letter the compliance audit of the Bicol university for the year ending December 31
2023 to the committee on public accounts letter dated July 29 2024 of the executive secretary Office of the
President malakanyang transmitting to original copies each of Republic Act number 12011 granting a franchise to Negros
electric and power corporation which was signed by the President to the archiv
letter dated August 2 2024 of the executive secretary Office of the President malakanyang transmitting two original copies each of Republic Act
numbers 12012 1213 12014 12015
12016 which were signed by the President to the Archives committee reports committee report number 1161 submitted
by the committees on science and technology appropriations and waste and means on House Bill 1073
committee report number 1162 submitted by the committee on government enterprises and privatization and house bill
1073 the commit and
rules majority leader Mr Speaker today being a Monday
and pursuant to our rules I mov that we open the privilege Please
proceed majority leader Mr Speaker I move that we recognize the honorable Representative Erwin t Tulfo of party
cis first privilege speach representative filimon Ms pares of the party natco Please proceed Sir
Sir um it is the honorable Representative Tulfo
Mr Speaker distinguish colleagues and fellow Filipinos the moment
Congressman majority leader we have representative Erwin p Tulfo cis act
cis Thank you please proceed sir my apologies I stand before you today
for the ofs of fip workers and businesses Whose livelihoods are at
risk the issue I bring to the floor Today is one of great importance an issue that if left un
address could lead to the loss of countless jobs the closure of many businesses and the undermining of our
econom integr speaker we have Witness a tring trend in
the r substandard and counterfeit products flooding our market particularly online
platforms like shopee and Lazada these products of which originate
from offshore sources espcially China are being sold at prices so low that they have started to undercut local
businesses businesses that pay the right taxes follow our regulations and employ hundreds of thousands of
Filipinos Mr Speaker Let us be clear This is not just an issue of
competition This is an issue of fairness and survival the presence of these substandard and counterfeit products has
created an even playing field where legitimate local manufacturer
do not sa ands this goods are sold at prices that
are impossible for any lawful business to match forcing therefore our local
enterprises to operate at a loss or worse to shut down entirely just this past we Mr Speaker My
office was approached by representatives from various local manufacturers companies such as American
home Asahi astron camel Caribbean carrier conception condura cool daddy
dowel yurika fujidenzo Hanabishi carlson kowa Ken locks midea Nikon Nova shark
Ninja tefal Tiger TF Mama union and 3D Mr Speaker these are not just names These are the companies that provide
jobs to over 300,000 Filipino workers These are the companies that contribute to our economy uphold our
laws and ensure that their products are safe for every Filipino household Mr Speaker I know you have a
heart for the workers imagine the devastation if these companies were to close down imagine the impact on the
Families of those 300 workers who would suddenly find themselves without a source of income It
will be another problem for our government Where to find work for these people the loss would beur and the blame
would not rest only to those selling substandard and discrepancy and enforcement is not just an oversight It
is a Crisis Mr Speaker the Department of trade and industry and the bure of customs must be
held accountable for allowing this products to enter our market on check we
cannot allow our local businesses to be decimated by the influx of unregulated and of Safe
products Mr Speaker I am not against online selling i recognize the
convenience and opportunity it brings especially in a world increasingly reliant on digital transactions
however this inconvenience or this convenience must not come at the expense of our lw our businesses and Our
workers online platforms must be h to the same standards as any other businesses operating in our country they
must ensure that the product sold Through Their sites comply with our regulations and that the sell are h
accountable today Mr Speaker I join my colleagues in cis party Congressman edv
kop benget representative Eric kop Quezon City second District representative Ralph wendel Tulfo and Uh
for filing a resolution and Congresswoman jocely Tulfo in filing a resolution to conduct a thorough inquiry
into this Unfair online sales practices this investigation Mr Speaker will seek
to Uncover how these products are entering our market Why They are not being regulated and
what immediate steps we can take to protect our local businesses and workers
Mr Speaker distinguished colleagues the time to act is now we must not Wait
until more businesses close their doors and more Filipinos lose their jobs We must stand together to ensure that our
market remains fair our product remains safe and Our economy remains strong Let
us not allow substandard and counterfeit goods to destroy the livelihood of our people Let us All together Mr Speaker
join together and help us pass This law to protect our in or support this
resolution to make it a law to protect our industries our workers especially
who are close to your heart Mr Speaker In Our nation Thank you and May we all work together for the betterment of the
Filipino people Thank you Mr Speaker Thank you also representative Erwin titol for partilist act cis majority
leader please Mr Speaker I now move that we recognize representative filimon Ms pares of party list co of natco for his
privilege speech fus person filimon Ms pares of part of natco Please proceed
Sir Mr Speaker esteem colleagues Magandang hapon sa ating lahat I rise today on the
on a matter of personal and collective privilege on behalf of the cooperative movement I would like to reiterate our
strong support to the public transportation transport modernization program or the PT
amid calls from the colleagues in the Senate to suspend the program
implementation the pmt aims to serve best interest by ensuring safe and comfortable
transportation providing reasonable daily wages for drivers without compromising affordability for our
commuters and of course What every Filipino demands the reduction of
traffic congestion through Road rationalization Mr Speaker with all your
respect the call of some Lakers for a suspension would not only negate the big
strides the program has made but it will also defeat the momentum and the
accomplishment we have achieve as of April 2024
83.8 or
160,000 66 ang mga UV express Mayon na rin pong nabuong
[Musika]
1,749 cooperatives na may mahigit 262 800 na miyembrong kaakibat dito at
mayroon na ring 1088 na mga korporasyong nabo as of July 31 of
2024 ang tumatakbong modernized unit ay nasa
1117 na at nag-uumpisa pa lang tayo dito again Mr Speaker another suspension
which will be the 8 since 2007 will only cause
distrust among our stakeholders and will Slow Down any progress that we have already made a suspension will certainly
affect and discourage the 2628 individual members who are already
in a cooperative and those have form corporations it will only affect their
loans their livelihood and their income Why is it that those who have
complied with the pmt requirements and have heed the government
calls should be penalized and be given a heavier burden than those who have not
on the other hand Mr Speaker We Want Is for our operators and driver to live
comfortably and be protected for example those who have consolidated are already
receiving regular pay and Social Security protection and benefits among others indeed the program's benefits
outweigh the cost contrary to to the fears of some of our countrymen We must also consider the public funds that have
already been allotted and spent by the D and its affiliated agencies for capacity building technical service assistance
and compliance monitoring we all know the challenges faced during this transition period are
not easy that is why cooperatives play a crucial role in this endeavor as they
have consistently shown their commitment to public service and cooperativism throughout the
Years while they face various challenges in accessing loans establishing their own fit management hiring personnel and
meeting regulatory and compliance requirements they have put their trust and confidence in pump that it will not
only benefit them but It also commuting public and the country as a whole this
collective efforts are already too Great to sacrifice for isolated cases of
dissatisfaction we should not judge the effectiveness of the program based on the complaints of a few as President
bungbong Marcos up stated why we should let the 20% control the voice of the
majority who have already consol and who have emb this program with that being said I wish to
express my gratitude and utmost appreciation to the President bungbong Marcos for his strong directive and
political will to continue the ptmp despite the pressures to suspend it in
the end this is one of the moments Where we as Lakers must work hand in hand with
the executive department to realize the noble intentions of the ptmp in laying down the foundation of an improved
transportation system ultimately leading to a better quality of life for every
Filipino the Filipino people deserve nothing less than progress and the cooperative movement is more than really
to support that therefore We must continue ptmp without any further
suspension again thank you very much Mr Speaker at mabuhay ang kilusang kooperatiba sa
Pilipinas Maraming maraming salamat Cong person filimon Ms pares part Nat and
chairman majority leader please Thank you Mr Speaker I move May i move that the
hon Erwin honer motion to spe as stated
obje leer Mr Speaker I to recognize the honorable Representative frz El Castro of part
teachers Fr cro teachers
Thank you Mr Speaker Magandang araw ginong speaker Sa mga kapwa ko kinatawan
at sa ating mga kababayan ngayong buwan ay ipinagdiriwang natin ang buwan ng wika na may temang Filipino wikang
mapagpalaya ang temang ito hindi lamang isang paggunita kundi isang panawagan para sa pagkilala sa mahalagang papel ng
ikang Filipino bilang kasangkapan ng kalayaan at pagbabago sa ating lipunan
ngunit may kinakaharap na problema ngayon ang wikang Filipino at iba't iba pang mga ah rehiyonal na wika so pag
sinabi nating a wikang Filipino ah Mr chair we are referring to other Regional
languages ayon sa ating konstitusyon ang paggamit ng mga rehiyonal na wika sa mga paaralan ay
pinahihintulutan kasama ng Ingles at ang Filipino ang desisyong ito ay kinilala ng korte suprema noong 2018 na nagsasaad
na ang paggamit ng mother tong bilang pangunahing medium sa pagtuturo ay alinsunod sa mga probisyon ng ating
konstitusyon Ganito rin ang sinasabi ng ating pandaigdigang kasunduan na ating nilagdaan at
Kinikilala ang karapatan ng mga bata mga katutubo at mga taong may kapansanan na
matuto sa kanilang sariling wika Ngunit sa kabila ng mga ito ang ating MTB mle mother tong based
multilingual Education ay tila nahaharap ngayon sa panganib na tuluyan ng alisin
ang hakbang na ito ay hindi lamang paglabag sa ating mga international obligations at kus Ngunit isa ring
hakbang na magalis ng mga tagumpay na nakamit turo sa unang wika ng mga
mag-aaral ang ating mga kabataan ay mas mahusay na natututo at mas masaya sa
pag-aaral kapag ang kanilang sariling wika ang ginagamit sa klase dahil mas
naiintindihan nila ito at sa ganito rin ah Mr Speaker napapa ah nabibigyang laya
sila na kung ano man yung kanilang mga idea Ay kanilang itong masabi sa mga
kinatawan walang ebidensya na nagpapakita na ang paglimita sa pagtuturo gamit lamang ng Ingles at
Pilipino ay nagpapabuti sa kalidad ng edukasyon sa katunayan Kinikilala ng mga
eksperto gaya ng World Bank na mas mainam ang MTB mle sa pagpapahusay ng Ed
hinihikayat natin ang dep ed na ipagpatuloy ang mga naumpisahang tagumpay at isulong ang prinsipyo ng
inclusive at karapatan sa edukasyon para sa lahat dapat tiyakin ng DepEd na ang mga batang nagsasalita ng ibang wika ay
makakatanggap ng nararapat na suporta sa kanilang sariling wika dapat ding panatilihin ang mother
tong bilang asignatura mula Kindergarten hanggang grade 3 at paunlarin pa ito upang maging bahagi ng isang
komprehensibong programang pangwika na nagtitiyak ng multilingual at ah multi
literate na mga mag-aaral sa Pagtatapos na nanawagan tayo ng suporta sa mtf mtbmle hindi lamang bilang isang
programa kundi bilang isang mahalagang karapatan ng bawat batang Pilipino sa pamamagitan nito masisiguro natin ang
ating mga kabataan ay magkakaroon ng de kalidad at makabuluhang edukasyon Hwag nating Hayaan na ang mga pinaghirapan
nating tagumpay para sa ating mga kabataan ay mapunta sa wala ang aming paninindigan ay isang pagtugon sa tawag
ng panahon bilang mga tagapagtanggol ng kalidad ng edukasyon para sa lahat Maraming salamat Mr Speaker at muli
Magandang hapon sa ating lahat majority leader
Madam speaker May we recognize the honorable kimer Olaso the first District
representative of Zamboanga City interpellation the honorable
recognize Good morning madam speak Good afternoon Madam speaker Thank you so much for recognizing me
Umo interpolate pertaining Department of Education Yung mother tong language natulad ng
binanggit niyo po kanila from Kinder until gr 3 Madam speaker I think Madam
speaker kung pwede po ibalik ng deet not only from Kinder to grade 3 Gawin nating
hanggang grade 6 Kasi karamihan ngayon sa mga kabataan sa ating lungsod most specially Zamboanga City zamb m City we
have I think about six dialect the people are speaking Chabacano tusuk Bisaya
Ilonggo Yakan and badiao and Samal so Alam niyo po
karamihan ngayon karamihan ngayon sa zambuanga city dahil tinanggal ng dep it
Yung mother tang language h na po hindi na po marunong magsalita ngayon yung mga
bata na Chabacano they could not even speak Chabacano anymore some of them they could not speak even ta because most of the
children English na iung pinagsasalita even Tagalog they have difficulties that's why Uh my interpolation there
was not only until grade 3 but but from Kinder until grade 6 Madam Cher That's
all Madam Cher Thank you so much mad mam Cher so Salamat po no kay
representative from Zamboanga tungkol doon sa ating binanggit yung binanggit niya na pagsuporta doon sa mother tang
at mtle no na mga ah wika na pangrehiyon na dapat na i-maintain natin dahil Ako
nga po Mr Madam chair ah Madam speaker ako po ay ah Ilocano ang aking nanay
tatay ay Ilocano lumaki ng Maynila Pero pero gusto ko sadang Mak makapag-aral ano noong mas malalim na mga salita sa
Ilocano k Alam ko lang communication ng Ilocano Pero mas maganda rin siguro na mapag-aralan yung ano no yung at
makintal sa utak ng ating mga kabataan lalong-lalo na doon sa Early Years yong pagmamahal doon sa kanilang sariling or
rehyon rehiyonal na wika ' ba So at samantalang pong meron tayong mga
subject na nagtuturo ng ibang wika hindi lang engl Madam ah speaker tinuturo din
ito sa senior high yung iba pang mga wika pero yung wika natin na yung wikang rehiyon ay hindi po nabibigyan ng
importansya So kaya nga sinabi natin sa ating ano no sa ating ah privilege speech na dapat ay i-review
pag-aralan kung paanong itong mother tong language natin ay ah maibabalik kund man ay magkaroon ng ah Sometime o
time sa ating curriculum ah Mula kinder hanggang grade 3 or hanggang grade 6 para naman po ano ma-maintain natin o
magkaroon talaga tayo ng ating mga kabataan na biyasa doon sa kanilang rehiyonal na
Wika Madam Madam speaker Uh Thank you for
allowing me na kalimutan kong banggitin kanina ah meron pa po tayong mga Yakan
and subanen Language ngayon po dahil sa modernization because of modern technologies
gadgets nawawala na po ito kaya sabi ko nga napakaimportanteng malaman ng ating mga Regional directors ng bawat
Department of educations na tawag natin kalahok natin sa gobyerno
they should they should return this back isauli to kasi p Hindi po most espcially
Chabacano the only tinatawag natin Chabacano speaking language most
likely 60% to Spanish in Mindanao is only Zamboanga City nawawala na po ang Chabacano ngayon kasi unti-unti na po
kinakain yung salit Chabacano unti-unti na p Nawawala ang dito kapag may Mayon
tayong bagong mandato galing sa Department of Education tanggalin ' so bigla na lang Natatanggal yung mga tulad
ng sinasabi ni Cong Resan yung mga salitang ano local language natin ang
pinakamasakit diyan kapag ang Regional Director natin ibang tribo gusto niya yung tribo niya lang ang pagsasalitain
sa eskwelahan Ayaw niyang pagsalitain whatever is the mother tong of the certain District or the certain ano area
dapat sana kung ano talaga yung mother tong ng certain area yun dapat sana ang pinagsasalita sa mga kabataan natin
ngayon believe me or not in another 20 years unti-unti ng mawawala Actually
most likely hindi lang unti mawawala na yung salitang Chabacano because in Zamboanga City Right now I'm so surprised as a as I grew up in Zamboanga
City mostly of the children from um 1 year old to 10 years old they could not speak Chabacano anymore karamihan is
English na nawawalan na po eh Kaya kailangan nating ang tulong ng ating Department of Education na ibalik ito at
do it as compulsary Madam Cher from Kindergarten until grade 6 yun lang po maraming salamat po Mr Cher Thank you
God bless majority leader
speaker I move that we refer the privilege speech and interpellation to the committee on
rules Priv spe of Congress is there objection hearing none
Motion is approved speaker I move that we suspend session for few minutes
majority leader kindly repeat it please Mr Speaker I mve that we suspend session for a few minutes session
suspended
s er
Liling
session resume majority leader please Mr Speaker I move that we recognize the honorable Serio the go of APEC party list first
privilege speech Cong recognize Thank you Mr Speaker Good
afternoon everyone Mr Speaker I rise on matters of personal and
collective privilege regarding an issuance of the Department of Energy governing the wholesale
electricity spot market Which has a very alarming provisions
regarding What the term as line rental i
decided br up this matter in this afternoon
plenary because the result of the computation of Region 8 and region
6 the electricity cost of those areas for the June and July billing rise up
from Php 85 centos to PH 67 centos per
kilowatt hour para po sa kaalaman ng lahat ang line rental po na nasa
provison ng wholesale electricity spot market ay nangyayari po kapag ka ang
linya ng national Grid Corporation of the Philippines or yung transmission line ay nagkakaroon ng congestion ang
ibig sabihin hindi po niya kayang i- transmit yung kuryente sa kabila papunta po doon
sa kabila halimbawa yung area ng Region 6 Region 8 kung Mayon po silang kontrata
na planta galing sa Luzon or sa mindanao Aton
constraint transmission line kadaan So yung mga planta sa lugar naon ang
nagsu-supply at under the Rolls magkakaroon po ng additional na bayad
ang mga Consumer sa area na Ian with the term as line rental I am questioning
that Mr Speaker Bakit nagrerenta yung mga tao
po ng lahat yung linya na yan sa umpisa ay pag-aari ng goberno it is an asset of
the national power corporation whena was passed in 2001 inilipat po siya sa
National transmission corporation or transco ngayon pinon po siya
pinaparentahan sa isang private entity National grade Corporation of Philippines ibig sabihin sa umpisa
pagmamay-ari na po ng estado o ng Pilipinas ang linya na yan ngayon habang mayong
concessioner every single centavo na ginagastos ng national grade Corporation
of the Philippines para i-extend at i-enhance i-upgrade yung linya na yan ay
singil-singil po sa ating lahat kasi yung mga infrastructure
energy regulatory Commission in form transmission development atung kaakibat
naon na amount parao lya naan sinisingil saong electricity consumers ng Pilipinas
and again pag
kung ang ating ginagamit na kuryente sa ating bahay ay dadaan sa linya na yan
mula sa planta na nagenerate ng kuryente na yan nakakontrata ng ating mga distribution utility ay nagbabayad na
naman po tayo ng transmission charge kaya sa electric bill natin makikita natin yung number to item transmission
charge Ngayon kung may problema yung linya dahil maliit yung alambre hindi naupgrade
hindi makadaan yung kontrata sa kabilang planta doon sa
gagamit sa kabila ay nagbabayad na naman tayo ng R line rental in accordance with
the provisions of that circular governing the wholesale electricity spot market that provision Mr ch is very
alarming That's why we Ser Look into that and I am uring our
colleagues in this chamber to look into that this representation will Later on file a house resolution in aid of
investigating that particular circular in aid of legislation kasi sobra sobra na po yung mga sinisingil natin na
bayaran sa kuryente lamang nung mga mayari ng planta papunta
lamang sa kanila yung lahat ng ating binabayad Wala naman po sa batas Yan that is a m issuance of the government
agencies regulating the power industry so Sana po ay Bibigyan natin ng pansin I would like to reiterate in the case of
Region 6 and Region 8 for the June and July billing the
amount add elc bill ranges ph5
to 67 per kil hour imagine that so I hope that we can do something about
that Mr Speaker Maraming salamat magandang hapon Maraming salamat Cong
person leader speaker ive that we refer the privilege speech of the honorable Dag to the committee on rules There's a
motion to refer the privileged speech of APEC Mar Congressman any objection hearing none
motions approve majority leader Mr Speaker I move that we Close the privilege hour There's a motion to close
the privilege hour any objection hearing none motion approve Priv is therefore terminated majority leader Mr Speaker
move that we acknowledge the guests of the honorable ker Adan Olaso from the first District of Zamboanga City they
are from Zone 4 of Zamboanga City they are Kagawad laya Ismael Kagawad fhana
juhan Kagawad misal tan and Barangay staff su lumong I so move Mr
Speaker Thank you to the guests of honorable kir
Adan Olaso mm representative of the first District of Zamboanga City to Zone 4 Zamboanga
City Welcome to the house of
representatives Saan sila there we St
this majority leader majority leader Mr Speaker I
would like to suspend session for a few minutes majority
leader Mr Speaker I move to suspend session for a few minutes Okay session
suspended
l
h
session resume majority leader please Mr Speaker I move that we proceed with additional reference of business and the secretary general be directed to read
the tits of the bills and resolutions for first reading as well as commit reports and communications so Mr Speaker Thank you majority leaders secretary
general Please proceed additional reference of business resolutions house resolution
1899 congratulating and loading Carlos yo for winning two medals in the men's
artistic gymnastics compe at the 2024 Olympic Games by representative migel the comm rules house resolution
1900 strongly urging the Fi health to implement another round of 30% increase in all benefit packages and coverage
taking into account the reported ex funds of the agency represent Lee
resolution 1901 congratulating nesty peso for winning the bronze medal in women's boxing at the Paris 2024
Olympics commit rules house resolution 1902 congratulating and commending Filipino
tennis player Alex iyala for bringing Honor To The Philippines through her exceptional Achievement in winning the 2024 open araba and feminino tournament
in Spain by representative Rodriguez rufus to the committee on youth sports development house resolution
1903 directing the proper house committee to conduct an inquiry on dof circular
0032 which among others allows unutilized fans of the pH health worth 89.9 billiones to be remitted to the
unprogrammed appropriations of the national budget by representative Rodriguez rufus to the committee rules house resolution 1904
congratulating and commending phip American athlete Lee Kiefer for winning the gold medal in women's foil at 2024
summer Olympics in France may representative Rodriguez rufus the committee on rules house resolution 1905
commending and congratulating nesty peso for winning the bronze medal in the women's 57 kgr boxing event at the 2024
Paris Olympic Games by representative puno the committee on rules house resolution 1906 expressing The Great
pride and joy of Filipinos in the bronze medal won by nesty peso in the 57 kgr division of women's boxing of the 2024
summer Olympic Games in France by representative Tolentino the committee on rules house resolution 1907 expressing profound Congratulations and
commendation to Carlos yulo for winning two gold medals in the gymnastics floor exercise and vault events in the 2024
Paris Olympics by representative anano Dizon to the committee rules house resolution 190 8 directing the house
committee on natural resources to conduct an investigation on the construction of illegal structures and persistence of quarrying operations in
the upper Marikina watershed which potentially contributed to the severe flooding in various parts of metro manila during typon karina by
representatives Brosas Castro Franz and Manuel the committee on rules house resolution 1909 congratulating and
commending boxer Ira Villegas for winning bronze medal in semifinals of the women's 50 kgr boxing event at the
2024 Paris Olympics by representative Olivarez the committee on rules house resolution 1910 expressing profound
condolences of the house on the demise of mother lily monteverde by representative Olivarez the committee on rules house
resolution 1911 congratulating and commending boxer Nest peso for winning bronze medal in semifinals of the
women's 57 kg boxing event at the 2024 Paris Olympics by representative Olivarez to the committe on rules house
resolution 1912 urging the appropriate committee to conduct an inquiry on the Unfair online sales practices of offshore appliance bronch shipping
directly to the Philippines and the enforcement discrepancies in relation there Two by representatives tool for Erwin tool for Ral wendel Yap edvic and
Yap Eric to the committee on rules house resolution 1913 congratulating and commending Filipino box aa Villegas for
her exemplar performance in winning a bronze medal in the women's 50 kgr division event at the 2024 Paris
Olympics by representative plato the comm on rules house resolution 1914 congratulating and commending
Filipino boxer nesty peso for her exemplar performance in winning a bronze medal in the women's 57 kilogram division event at the 2024 Paris
Olympics by representative plo to the committee on rules house resolution
1915 resolution congratulating and conferring the Congressional Medal of distinction to nesty alcaide Peso for
winning the bronze medal for the Philippines in the women's 57 kgr boxing event during the 2024 Paris Olympics
held in Roland Garo stadium Paris France by representatives romales Ferdinand Martin Gonzalez Aurelio Suarez dalipe
libanan Marcos romald yeda Marie and as committee on rules house resolution
1916 resolution congratulating and conferring the Congressional Medal of distinction to Ira Cordero Villegas for winning the bronze medal for the
Philippines in the women's 50 kgr boxing competition during the 2024 Paris summer Olympics held in Roland Garo stadium
Paris France by representatives romales Ferdinand Martin Gonzalez Aurelio Suarez dalipe libanan Marcos romal
marid rules house resolution 1917 resolution congratulating and commending the medal winners and the
entire Philippine delegation for their phenomenal and historic performance during the 2024 Paris summer Olympics by
representative romales Ferdinand Martin Gonzalez Aurelio Suarez dalipe libanan Marcos romal Mar
Andre rules lead than majority
leader majority leader Mr Speaker we are in receipt of
the conference committee report on the disagreeing provisions of House Bill number 9713 and Senate bill number
2455 on the self-reliant Defense posture revitalization act
Mr Speaker I move for the
[Musika]
ratification session suspended yan
pantay oh
this session resume majority leader state your motion please Mr Speaker um we are in receit of the conference
committee report and the disagreeing provisions of House Bill number 9713 and Senate bill number 2455 on the
self-reliant Defense posture revitalization act Mr Speaker in accordance with the rules I move to ratify the said conference committee
There's a motion to ratify said conference committee report Is there any objection the chair here is not the
motion is approved all those in favor conference committee report please please say I
I all those against it say n the eyes have it the conference
committee report on the proposed self reliant defense posture
this Yeah act is ratified
majority leader please Mr Speaker I move that we consider house resolution number 1915
and may as a secretary general to read the title of the said resolution secretary general Please proceed house resolution
1915 resolution congratulating and conferring the Congressional Medal of distinction to Nest Al peto for winning
the bronze medal for the Philippines in the women's 57 kgr boxing event during the 2024 Paris Olympics held in Roland
Garo stadium Paris France majority
leader Mr Speaker I move for the adoption of house resolution 1915 in consolidation with house resolutions
1901 1905 1906 1911 and 1914
Thank you majority leader There's a motion to adopt said consolidation of house resolutions all those in favor say
i hi all those not in favor or against it say the eyes have it the adoption of
said as as house resolution 1901
1905 1906 1911 1914
in consolidation of this one 195 adopted majority leader please Mr
Speaker I mve that we consider house resolution number 1916 and may ask the secretary general to read the title of the said resolution secretary general
Please proceed house resolution 1916 resolution congratulating and conferring the Congressional Medal of
distinction to AA Cordero Villegas for winning the bronze medal for the Philippines in the women's 50 kgr boxing
competition during the 2024 Paris summer Olympics held in Roland Garo stadium Paris
France majority leader Mr Speaker I move for the adoption of house resolution 1916 in consolidation with house
resolutions 1889 1891 189 1896 1898 1909
and 19 13 There's a motion to consolidate house resolution 19
1916 stated 1889 1891 188 95 1896 all those in favor say
i all those against it and the eyes have
it house resolution 1916 is consolidation of Uh 18 89
1891 18 95 1896 hereby approved and adopted Ge
leader please Mr Speaker I move that we consider house resolution 1917 and may ask the secretary general to read the title of the said resolution secretary
general Please proceed house resolution 1917 conr resolution congratulating and
commending the medal winners and the entire Philippine delegation for their phenomenal and historic performance
during the 2024 Paris summer Olympics majority leader Mr Speaker I move for the adoption of house
resolution 1917 in consolidation with house resolution 1887 There's a motion
to um to adopt house resolution 1917 in consolidation with house resolution
1887 all those in favor say i all those against it say
guys Have It house resolution 1917 in consolidation with house resolution 1887 is here by
adopted majority leader Mr Speaker last Wednesday August 7 2024 we adopted house resolution number
1864 congratulating and conferring the Congressional Medal of excellence to Carlos adriel Pulo for winning two Gold
medals for the Philippines in the men's artist gymnastics floor exercise finals and vault apparatus finals during the
2024 Paris summer Olympics held in the bcy arena Paris France I move for the
consolidation of similar measures namely house resolution numbers 174
1875 1878 1879 1881
1882 1884 1886 188 8 1890
1893 189 1899 and 1907 with house resolution
number 1864 ISO move Mr Speaker There's a motion to consolidate as stated all
those in favor or against it say
okay Is there any objection the chair here is None motion as stated is here by
consolidated and adopted thank you majority
leader Mr Speaker I mve that we adjoin session until 3:00 p.m. tomorrow august
13 s join till tomorrow august
13 3 pm
[Musika]